בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף לג, daf lamed
gimmel, 33. Yes, that's a new way to know the דף. daf.
It's the number of the day in July plus 30. Okay, good.
Anyway, so good ערב erev 4th of July. We pick up at
the bottom of לב עמוד ב. lamed bet amud bet.
And we are up to
where is it?
איכא
ד... ika de... wait a minute... Okay, alright. רב פפא משמיה דרבא
מתני לה ארישא. Rav Pappa mishme deRava matni leh a-reisha. It is
3, 4, 5, 8 lines from the bottom, middle of the line.
Basically, we are dealing with a משנה, mishna, very important. The earlier
משניות mishnayot talked about people crashing into each other in רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim and said that they're פטור patur because they were going
with רשות, reshut, which
even one guy running and one guy walking, which is interesting. But
anyway, that gave the appearance or
that אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik would be פטור patur if he's operating
in רשות, reshut, with רשות, reshut, with permission to be doing what
he's doing. But the משנה mishna we just read clearly contradicts that
because the משנה mishna we just read talks about chopping wood in
your backyard, in your private domain, and it goes ahead and a
splinter goes and hits somebody else in their property. So you're operating
in רשות, reshut, it's flying off not even into a רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim but to private property, and you're חייב. chaiyav. So obviously
operating with רשות reshut is not enough to exempt an אדם המזיק.
Adam Hamazik. So the difference just to clarify, taken on its own,
we could have said that the reason in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
that you're פטור, patur, it's sort of like, and this is actually
worth underscoring for a moment, we didn't make this point yesterday, it's
sort of like the idea that שן ורגל shen ve-regel is exempt
in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, right? You could have sort of said
that the reason is, you know, if in order to give people
the ability to use רשות הרבים reshut harabbim first of all, you
can't make them liable for everything or then nobody would use it.
And maybe more so, you know, if I'm using רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim and I know other people are using רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
like I have a responsibility to be watching out for myself. And
if I'm not watching out for myself, you know, maybe it's פי
הניזק, pi-ha-nizak, maybe it's contributory negligence. You might have said that that
was the difference, right? So if everybody's using רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
everybody's sort of got to watch out for themselves. The גמרא Gemara
however emphasized a different point, that in the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
both people were moving, and since both people were moving and nobody
was particularly more to blame than the other person, then you cannot
sort of say one person is the מזיק mazik and the other
person is ניזק. nizak. Why do you say that I was the
one that I got my fist into your face, you got your
face into my fist? Now that would be, you know, why do
I say I got my beam into your pitcher, you got your
pitcher into my beam? So anyway, but that's important that we had
some exemptions of אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik when it was in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, when it was in the public thoroughfare because everybody's
operating with רשות, reshut, but it's important to note that that's not
a blanket exemption because we had our case in our משנה mishna
of chopping wood and the splinters go flying, and even though you're
allowed to be doing what you're doing, you're going to be חייב.
chaiyav. And it certainly
look, it should be no worse than the case of בור, Bor,
when you dump your garbage or you spill out your water in
רשות הרבים reshut harabbim even if you have permission to do it,
you're responsible. So having permission is not enough to be exempt. Okay,
so that was some basic principles about אדם המזיק. Adam Hamazik. And
then but recently we're dealing now in the גמרא Gemara with this
idea of somebody chopping wood and somebody coming in and the wood
flying and killing the person, and the גמרא Gemara actually said that
he's going to be exempt even if he gave permission for the
person to come in. So that seems like wild, why would you
be exempt? You know somebody's in your store, you gave them permission.
And the גמרא Gemara basically said because you could be exempt from
גלות, galus, going into exile, not only if you're not negligent enough
but if you're too negligent, if you're שוגג קרוב למזיד. shogeg karov
l'meizid. And the גמרא Gemara challenged that yesterday. Okay so now we're
going to have another read on that. So let's take a look,
again eight lines from the bottom, רב פפא משמיה דרבא מתני לה
ארישא Rav Pappa mishme deRava matni leh a-reisha taught that teaching about
being exempt on the first part of the ברייתא. braita. הנכנס לחנותו
של נגר שלא ברשות, Ha-nichnas l'chanut shel nagar she-lo birshut, somebody who
goes in to the store of the carpenter without permission, וניתזה לו
בקעת וטפחה לו על פניו, venitiz lo bikzah vetaphah lo al panav,
and a splinter flies and hits him in his face, on his
forehead, ומת umet and he dies, פטור, patur, he's exempt. So in
that case, אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, amar Rabbi Yose bar Chanina,
חייב בארבעה דברים ופטור מגלות. chaiyav be-arba'ah devarim u-patur mi-galus. In that
case they're exempt from גלות galus because that case the carpenter was
unaware that the guy came in. Actually there's an interesting discussion תוספות
Tosfot has. Was he aware but he didn't give him permission or
was he completely unaware? But anyway, but that case at least the
guy didn't have permission to be there. So there he's exempt from
גלות, galus, but he is חייב chaiyav in ארבעה דברים. arba'ah devarim.
Now this actually still creates a problem because חייב chaiyav in ארבעה
דברים arba'ah devarim if you might remember, when we say אדם מועד
לעולם, Adam muad l'olam, that's for נזק. nezek. The obligation for the
ארבעה דברים arba'ah devarim for שבת, shevet, צער, tza'ar, נזק... nezek... like
flat across the board except we've had some challenges to that. But
the other extra payments for חבלה chavalah is only for פשיעה. peshiah.
And the payments for בושת boshet is only with intention to damage.
Okay, so if you're saying חייב בארבע דברים, chayav b'arba devarim, it
means you were negligent. If you were negligent, it means even if
the guy came in without permission, presumably you saw him there. So
if you're negligent, it's—we're still back to the question about why are
you פטור patur from גלות? galut? Okay, so רש״י Rashi says it's
not because of too much negligence, it's not because of too little
negligence. The reason you're exempt from גלות galut is an arbitrary reason.
It's not דמיא דיער. damya d'yaar. Right, the classic case in the
תורה Torah is two people going into a forest to chop wood.
And there, they both have permission to be there. So this would
be an arbitrary exclusion. If a guy doesn't have permission to be
there, even if you're aware of his presence and even if you're
negligent, you're פטור מגלות. patur migalut. Okay, so strange idea, but that's
the way רש״י Rashi explains this because once we're saying חייב בארבע
דברים, chayav b'arba devarim, we are conceding the fact that there is
negligence in this case. One minute, let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay, מאן דמתני לסיפא, man d'matni l'seifa, if you say you
are exempt from גלות galut in the end case when you gave
the guy permission, right? So כל שכן רישא, kol sheken reisha, you're
certainly going to be exempt in the—like that case what's like a
lot of negligence, so you would certainly be exempt in the first
case where the negligence was like less. Now it's not necessarily true,
like maybe too much is פטור patur but the right amount is
חייב. chayav. But anyway, but מאן דמתני לרישא, man d'matni l'reisha, but
if you say you're exempt in the first case when he came
in without permission, אבל סיפא, aval seifa, but in the end case,
כיון דברשות, keivan d'bireshut, חייב גלות. chayav galut. Since he has permission,
you are חייב גלות. chayav galut. So maybe you're exempt because you
don't have permission and that's not similar to the case of יער
yaar in the תורה, Torah, because it's a—you know, it's a formal
exception. You're not חייב chayav in גלות galut if the guy is
there without permission. But in the end when you gave him permission,
you're חייב גלות. chayav galut. And it does not have this idea
that if you have too much negligence, you're exempt. No, you'd be
חייב גלות. chayav galut. You knew he was there, he had permission,
you're חייב גלות. chayav galut. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ומי חייב גלות? umi chayav galut? Are you really חייב? chayav?
והתניא, vehatanya, we taught a ברייתא: braita: הנכנס לחנותו של נפח, hanichnas
lechanuto shel napach, you go into the store of a
metalworker, וניתזה ניצוץ וטפחה לו על פניו, venitzo nitzotz vetephacho lo al
panav, and a spark flies off and hits the guy in the
face, ומת, umet, and he dies, פטור, patur, he's exempt, ואפילו נכנס
ברשות, veafilu nichnas bireshut, even with permission. Okay, so there what do
you see? So there you see that you are exempt from גלות
galut even if you enter with permission. And this goes against, right,
what we're now saying. You're only exempt if the guy came in
without permission, but if he had permission, you're חייב גלות. chayav galut.
And here you say if he had permission, you're פטור. patur. So
again, like it's hard to understand what this is about, but here
again we have a guy entering with permission and going to be
פטור patur in גלות. galut.
Entered at your own risk.
Well right, but again, like what's the logic? How's this worse than
the case of יער? yaar? Again, maybe there's a case of like
too much fault. But anyway, but at least here you have that
case of coming in with permission and the guy being פטור patur
from גלות. galut. So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא במאי עסקינן בשוליה
דנפחא. hacha bemai askinan b'shulya d'napcha. We're dealing with—thank you—we're dealing with
the—what do you call it? I was going to say an intern
but that's not the right
word—apprentice of the ironworker. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: שוליה דנפחא,
shulya d'napcha, an apprentice? למקטליה קאי? lemiktalye kai? Just because he's your
apprentice, he's—you can kill him? That's a great line of the גמרא.
Gemara. Big deal, he's the apprentice and he has permission. Since when
does that get you off of גלות? galut? So the גמרא Gemara
says: לא, כשרבו מסרהב בו לצאת. lo, kisherabo mesarhev bo latzet. No,
the master is telling him, "Get out of here, get out of
here. I need to—I need to work in private." The person says,
"ואינו יוצא", veaino yotze he refuses to go. So the גמרא Gemara
says: ומשום דרבו מסרהב בו לצאת למקטליה קאי? umeshum derabo mesarhev bo
latzet lemiktalye kai? Just because the master is urging him to go,
he's allowed—you know, he's open to be killed? It still doesn't explain
it. Big deal. You know he's there. How come you're going to
be, and if you're—how come you're going to be פטור? patur? So
the גמרא Gemara says: לא, כסבור יצא. lo, kasavar yatza. No, he
figured, "I told him to go, he's gone." So it'd be a
case where—where he's no longer negligent. He figured that his apprentice listened
to him. The גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי אחר נמי? ei hachi
acher nami? So let that be true also about another person. You
know, you told him to go, you assume he's gone. No, אחר
לית ליה אימתא דרביה האי אית ליה אימתא דרביה. acher leit lei
eimata d'rabbeih hai it lei eimata d'rabbeih. Another person, I don't assume
that another person necessarily listens to me, but I assume my apprentice
did listen to me. Okay. So if he comes in שלא ברשות
shelo bireshut and then maybe I'm פטור, patur, maybe again it would
be a scenario where either I don't know that he's there or
I tell him to go and if anybody comes in without permission
and I tell them to go, then I assume they listened to
me and they left. Okay. So I'm not—so in that case, I'm
פטור patur either because it's not similar to the case of the
יער yaar or because it's without permission or because I assumed that
they're not there. But if they came in ברשות, bireshut, okay, then
in the case of an apprentice... You're still going to be פטור
patur because when you tell him to leave, you assume he's gone.
So it's a very narrow אוקימתא ukimta that it's doing about this.
Anyway, bottom line is we have these different ideas about why you'd
be פטור patur in גלות. galus. One is because of too much
negligence, even if he came in with permission, and another which is
no, like we don't have a פטור p'tur for too much negligence,
but you'd be פטור patur if he came in without permission, maybe
because, at least the way רש"י Rashi explains it, you can't say
there's no negligence in that case because you're חייב chayav in ד'
דברים. arba devarim. So presumably you know he's there. Okay, so so
there has to be some other exclusion from גלות galus and that's
the way רש"י Rashi explains just because it's not דומיא דיער, dumya
d'yaar, it's not parallel to the case of the forest in the
תורה. Torah. Yes, Charlie, you had a question? No, okay, moving on.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רזיד משמיה דרבא מתני לה
אהא. Razid mishmei de'Rava matni lah aha.
רזיד Razid in the name of רבא Rava taught this issue of
פטור p'tur from גלות, galus, not in the case of having permission,
not having permission, but in this other case. It says ומצא. u'matza.
It says, you know, that he's chopping wood and the handle flies
and the and the head flies off and it finds the guy
and kills him, the, you know, the head of the axe. So
פרט לממציא את עצמו. perat le'mamtzi es atzmo. So that's the head
of the axe found the guy, which would exclude a case of
a guy making, sort of getting himself found. What does it mean
getting himself found? כדתניא רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, K'detanya Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov, מי שיצאה אבן מתחת ידו, mi she'yatzah even mi-tachas yado, you
threw a rock, you know, into the רשות הרבים, reshus ha'rabim, or
slipped out of your hand or whatever it is, והוציא הלה את
ראשו, ve'hotzi halah es rosho, and it would have landed like and
not hurt anybody and this guy while the rock was in mid-flight
popped up his head. I mean he wasn't trying to hurt himself,
he didn't realize that there was a rock flying, but he moved
into the trajectory of the rock. Okay, וקיבלה, ve'kiblah, and as a
result he received the rock, the rock hit him. פטור, patur, you're
exempt. Okay, now is that you're exempt because you don't have enough
negligence? Not, doesn't sound like it. It sounds like another formal exemption.
You threw something in רשות הרבים. reshus ha'rabim. That was completely negligent.
It could have hit someone. But the, it did hit somebody, but
the way it hit somebody was not because that was the trajectory
of the rock when it left your hand, you know, if you
had followed that trajectory and it ended it would have, it would
have, you know, it would have hit the ground, but somebody moved
into its path. And there's an exception here that
if you move into the path then you are participating
somehow in, you know, sort of similar to like if two guys
crashing into רשות הרבים. reshus ha'rabim. You're actively participating in the act
of, you know, getting yourself, you know, of having this rock hit
you. In that case when the victim is an active participant, you
know, in making it happen, even if even if you were negligent
and he wasn't negligent, somehow that exempts you, that gets you off
the hook. Okay, if your pot was in the רשות הרבים reshus
ha'rabim and the guy threw the rock and the wind moved your
pot into the trajectory, is he פטור patur from נזק? nezek? No,
I don't know, you can't assume it's the same thing about נזק.
nezek. These are פסוקים pesukim specifically about what he call it. Like
just a minute ago we said that in the case of שלא
ברשות she'lo bi'reshus you're חייב chayav in ד' דברים arba devarim and
you're פטור patur in נזק? nezek? No, פטור patur in גלות.
galus. So there seems to be some of these arbitrary exemptions here
by by גלות. galus. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, now, and
in that case, אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yosi bar
Chanina, פטור מגלות וחייב בארבעה דברים. patur mi'galus ve'chayav be'arba devarim. Fine,
you're פטור patur in גלות galus but here you go, you're still
חייב chayav in ד' דברים arba devarim because you're still being negligent.
You're throwing something into רשות הרבים reshus ha'rabim and this guy, you
know, you know, is just walking normally, he might have walked into
the path, you know, but nevertheless he's not negligent, you're the one
that's negligent. Okay, so therefore it's again some formal exemption. It has
to be דומיא דיער, dumya d'yaar, the guy can't walk into the
path. But these are formal exemptions, you actually have negligence and you'd
be חייב chayav in ד' דברים. arba devarim. The גמרא Gemara says,
מאן דמתני להא כל שכן אהך קמייתא. man de'matni l'ha kol she'ken
a'hach kamaisa. If you say you're exempt in this case, you're certainly
exempt in, no רש"י Rashi says now we're not dealing with exemption
but חייב chayav in ד' דברים. arba devarim. If you say you're
חייב chayav in ד' דברים arba devarim here, you're certainly חייב chayav
in ד' דברים arba devarim in the earlier cases. אבל מאן דמתני
אקמייתא, aval man de'matni a'kamaisa, but if you say that you're חייב
chayav in the earlier cases, ד' דברים arba devarim when the guy
walks into your store, maybe you're aware that he's walking into your
store. Fine, there you have negligence. אבל הכא פטור לגמרי. aval hacha
patur legamre. In this case you're fully exempt. Why are you fully
exempt? So because apparently in this case that you, you know, you
were un-, maybe you didn't have negligence that a guy was going
to walk into the, you know, walk into the where the rock
had been thrown. Again, I don't really understand this because to me
it seems like everything is based on the particular circumstances of the
case. If I'm throwing something in רשות הרבים, reshus ha'rabim, then maybe
that is negligent and I, people are moving around and I have
to expect that somebody might move into its trajectory. So it's possible
רשות הרבים reshus ha'rabim does have negligence. It's possible in my store
I don't have negligence, maybe I wasn't aware that the guy was
there, right? So the assumptions that the גמרא Gemara are making, is
making, that in the case of the store you clearly have more
negligence and in this case you clearly have less, you know, again,
I don't exactly get what you know why. What? Yeah, that the
גמרא Gemara just assumes everything should be based on the particulars of
the case, right. So it was kind of to, to make an
אוקימתא ukimta for particulars of the case. Exactly. Right, but it's true,
it's true, yeah, I hear that. Right. Right. Right. Okay. Let's anyway,
but we got the idea that for ארבעה דברים Arba'ah Devarim you
need negligence and for גלות Galus either too much negligence exempts you
or some of these formal distinctions about entering שלא ברשות shelo birshus
or ממציא את עצמו mamtzi es atzmo and so on. All right,
תנו רבנן. Tnu Rabbanan. One more case of this or along these
lines. הפועלים שבאו לתבוע שכרן מבעל הבית. Ha-po'alim she-bau litbo'a s'charan mi-ba'al
ha-bayis. Workers came to go to the employer, the homeowner, there they
were, they were mowing his lawn or they were harvesting the field
and they came to get their money at the end of the
day. ונגחן שורו של בעל הבית, Ve-nig'chan shoro shel ba'al ha-bayis, and
they went into the guy's yard and they got gored by the
owner's ox. Okay, so again this is a question about who like
normally we say you if you go into my domain without permission,
right, so that's the one case that I'm exempt is you enter
into my your domain my domain without permission. Right, then it's שורך
ברשותי מה בעי, shore-cha birshuti mah ba'ei, who said you were allowed
to be here? I can't be liable for things that happen to
you if you're on my property without my permission. Okay, so that
seems to be the case. It's telling you that they don't have
permission to enter into his property even if they need to get
paid. All right, without explicit permission. Okay, ונגחן שורו של בעל הבית,
Ve-nig'chan shoro shel ba'al ha-bayis, ונשכן כלבו של בעל הבית, ve-nashchan kalbo
shel ba'al ha-bayis,
or the dog bites them, ומת, u-mes, and they die, פטור. patur.
So now we're going back also to the question of of what
do you call it? Of גלות, Galus, except not גלות, Galus, because
if they get gored or attacked by a dog, it's really the
question about right about paying a כופר. kofer. If my animal attacks
whatever you know somebody and kills them, it's a question about being
חייב chayav in a כופר. kofer. So it is funny that it
gave an example of dying, because a more an easier example would
just be am I חייב chayav normal נזק, nezek, you know, maybe
כופר kofer has different rules. Anyway, but the point basically is somebody
comes into my רשות, reshus, they get hurt by my animal, I'm
exempt. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, רשאים פועלים לתבוע שכרן מבעל הבית. resha'im
po'alim litbo'a s'charan mi-ba'al ha-bayis. No, the owner is not exempt because
people workers have their implicit permission, you know, they have the right
to go in and to ask to be paid. So therefore they
they have a right to be there and therefore the the owner
is not exempt. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דשכיח
במתא, I deshchiach be-masa, if the owner, you know, the guy who
owes them money is, you know, is often found in the city,
in the town, מאי טעמא דאחרים? mai ta'ama de-Acherim? Why do why
does this second position think that they have a right to go
in onto his property? Wait till you find him. He's in the
tavern, you'll find him in the town on a regular basis. Wait
till you who says you can go into his property without getting
permission? Okay, ואי דשכיח בביתא, ve-i deshchiach be-veisa, and if he's presumably
like only found in the house, they won't have an opportunity to
find him in the town, מאי טעמא דתנא קמא? mai ta'ama de-Tanna
Kamma? So what are you supposed to do? You didn't have telephones
in those days. So if the guy is always at home and
you need to get paid, of course you should be have a
right to go into his yard and knock on his door. Okay,
so what's the case where they could be debating whether they have
a right to be going into his yard? לא צריכא בגברא דשכיח
ולא שכיח, lo tzricha be-gavra deshchiach ve-lo shchiach, so the obvious is
a middle case. You know, sometimes he's a he's in the city
and sometimes he's not. Okay, so nevertheless there's a presumption that since
sometimes he's in the town, you can't just walk in unannounced. Okay,
so what happened though? So it doesn't just it's not just that
case. וקרא בבבא, Ve-kara be-vava, you call out at the door, you
say, "Hey, we're here we came to get paid." ואמר להו Ve-amar
le-hu אין, in, yes, I know you're there. Okay, hold on a
minute. Okay, maybe he didn't say it told them, he just said
yes. So what does yes mean? מר סבר Mar savar אין עול,
in ul, yes, fine, come in and I'll pay you. Okay, that's
what yes means. עול תוב משמע, ul tuv mashma, come up and
come in. ומר סבר U-mar savar אין, in, yes, I know you're
there, קום בדוכתך משמע, kum be-duchtach mashma, stay where you are, I'll
be down in a minute. All right, but basically the point being
that everybody agrees if you have a right to be there, either
because as a worker you have a right to be paid and
that's the only way you're going to get paid is by going
there because you can't get them outside of the house, or he
gave you permission, then obviously he's חייב. chayav. If you don't have
a right to be there, then he's going to be פטור. patur.
Okay, of course the other interesting question getting back to the fact
that the circumstances are always different is, what if it's unclear? Right,
what if like, let's say we could both agree that when he
said yes, it was intrinsically ambiguous. Right, does he have to prove
that you didn't have a right to be there? Do you have
to prove that you do have a right? How do you deal
with cases that you that that you're not going to be able
to resolve whether it's clear whether it's clear you had a right
or not? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, תניא כמאן
דאמר אין קום בדוכתך משמע, tanya ke-man de-amar in kum be-duchtach mashma,
we have a ברייתא braita that teaches it in this case yes
means yes stay there I'll be down in a minute. דתניא, De-tanya,
we taught a ברייתא. braita. נכנס לתבוע שכרו מבעל הבית, nichnas litva
s'charo miba'al habayis, a worker came to demand his payment from the
owner. ונגחו שורו של בעל הבית או נשכו כלבו פטור, u'nag'acho shoro
shel ba'al habayis o neshacho kalbo patur, and here it does not
have the ידיעה, yedi'a, right? The word died there seems strange, okay,
he was gored or bitten, the owner is exempt. אף על פי
שנכנס ברשות, af al pi shenichnas birshus, and this says even though
he came in with permission. This is sort of like the ברייתא
braisa before about the meadow worker where it says even though the
guy had permission you're exempt, it's crazy, right? It sounds like some
blanket exemption when you're on my property even with permission, which the
גמרא Gemara is not prepared to accept. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמאי פטור, amai patur, why are you exempt? You know, you have
permission to be there, why is the owner exempt? אלא לאו דקרי
אבבא ela lav dekari abava must be you called out on the
door, ואמרו ליה אין v'amru lei in and he said yes, ושמע
מינה אין קום דוכתך משמע ushma mina in kum duchtach mashma yes
means yes stay where you are I'll be down in a minute.
Of course the irony is then the ברייתא braisa still describes it
as, you know, נכנס ברשות. nichnas birshus. It's not נכנס ברשות, nichnas
birshus, it means נכנס nichnas with a presumption of having permission but
you were actually wrong, you actually didn't have permission. All right, anyway,
interesting case, again what's more in a way more interesting is not
that the גמרא Gemara has introduced any real new principles but that
the, you know, that the ברייתא braisa seemed to be saying making
sort of more blanket statements like anytime you're in my domain I'm
exempt from גלות galus and I'm exempt from נזק nezek and here
the גמרא Gemara has sort of reinterpreted: no, you really it was
really because I wasn't negligent or it was really because you didn't
have permission and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: now we actually, you know, these פרקים prakim have been
very like nicely divided, right? The first פרק perek was כללים, klalim,
the second פרק perek was שן ורגל shen v'regel although the last
משנה mishna on the second פרק perek was introduced אדם מועד לעולם,
adam muad l'olam, but until now we've basically been dealing with אדם
המזיק. adam hamazik. Okay, now so it has a nice coherent, but
now like I would like a new פרק perek to start right
here because now we're completely shifting gears and we're going to basically
like שור המזיק. shor hamazik. Okay, so let's take a look. Although
we still have a little bit of אדם. adam. שני שוורים תמים
שחבלו זה בזה, shnei shvarim tamim shechavlu zeh bazeh, you have two
tame oxen that gore one another. משלמין במותר חצי נזק, mishalmin bemotar
chatzi nezek, so one did a hundred dollars worth of damage and
the other did, let's say eighty dollars worth of damage. The difference
is twenty, so the one that inflicted the more damage pays half
of the difference, pays ten. Okay. שניהם מועדים, shneihem muadim, let' say
they're both מועד, muad, they're both habitual. משלמין במותר נזק שלם, mishalmin
bemotar nezek shalem, so one did a hundred, one eighty, the one
who did the more damage pays the difference, pays twenty. אחד תם
ואחד מועד, echad tam v'echad muad, one is תם tam and one
is a מועד. muad. מועד בתם, muad b'tam, now let's say the
מועד muad did more damage than the תם, tam, the מועד muad
did a hundred and the תם tam did eighty. משלמין במותר נזק
שלם, mishalmin bemotar nezek shalem, so you pay the difference, twenty, you
pay full. תם במועד, tam b'muad, if the תם tam did a
hundred and the מועד muad did eighty, so משלמין במותר חצי נזק,
mishalmin bemotar chatzi nezek, you pay the difference, twenty, you pay it
half, you pay ten. Now somebody, Charlie, should be jumping up and
down and making a very serious objection at this point. What's the
problem with what we just said? Until now it seems obvious. תוספות
Tosafot actually says I don't get it, this whole משנה mishna is
like so obvious, who needs this משנה? mishna? Of course you pay
the difference, like what's the חידוש, chiddush, right? Whatever the difference is
you pay it. If you're a מועד muad you pay the difference
full, if you're a תם tam you pay the מועד muad half.
What's the problem in this case?
A תם tam gored a hundred and the מועד muad gored eighty,
and it says okay, the תם tam did more, so the difference
is twenty, so pay half of the difference, pay ten. What's the
problem with that?
The תם tam should not be liable for the eighty if it's
a חצי. chatzi.
If the תם tam gored a hundred, the תם's tam liability is
fifty, right?
The
מועד's muad liability is eighty. You don't pay half the difference, you
halve the damage and then you figure it out, right? So what
does this mean that you pay half the difference? That's crazy, not
obvious, it's the opposite, it's crazy, okay? In a case of תם
tam and מועד. muad. In the case they're both תם, tam, they're
both מועד, muad, then it's pretty obvious, you figure out what the
difference is. But in the case of תם tam and מועד, muad,
you should figure out each one's individual damage, half of the תם,
tam, the full of the מועד, muad, and then you pay. So
the ראש Rosh says that's the חידוש chiddush of the משנה. mishna.
The חידוש chiddush of the משנה mishna is he says that it's
a case that they started at the same time. By the way,
here's another important point that the ראש Rosh makes. He says if
one of them starts, one of them is the
instigator, then the one who's reacting is totally פטור, patur, okay, because
it's basically כל המשנה באחר ושינה בו. kol hamishaneh b'acher v'shinah bo.
You can't blame the ox that was attacked for then attacking back.
Okay, so number one the ראש Rosh says this is only a
case where they both started at the same time and he says
the חידוש chiddush of the משנה mishna is that you don't say
there were two acts of damage here, you pay fifty, you know,
you did a hundred, you did eighty, so let's figure it all
out, no, you basically look at it as the only damage that
occurred was the difference in the damages, okay, which is a huge
חידוש, chiddush, right? But he basically... As they start fighting at the
same time, so you don't say this one did a hundred and
this one did eighty. You basically say this one did twenty of
damage on the other. Everything else evens out, it's like it didn't
happen, it net cancels itself out. That's a huge חידוש. chiddush. I
don't know the basis of saying such a thing. But that's exactly
what he says the חידוש chiddush is. Now תוספות Tosafot has another
related נפקא מינה. nafka mina. We're going to see in a minute
that there's a debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and רבי ישמעאל
Rebbe Yishmael when my תם tam gores your ox, okay, and let's
say it did a hundred dollars worth of damage, and I owe
you fifty. Do I just owe you fifty and you it's you
could collect from the ox if you wanted to or it's limited
to the value of the ox but I owe you fifty? Or
do you actually get fifty dollar stake in my ox? Okay, you
actually own fifty dollars of my ox. So if you say the
latter, there's also a חידוש chiddush here when our two תם tam
oxen gore one another, it shouldn't just be let's say mine did
more damage. So you now own ten dollars worth of my ox.
That really shouldn't be the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha should be
I owe forty dollars of your ox and you owe, oh not
owe, I own excuse me, it shouldn't just be that you own
ten dollars, if there was twenty dollar difference, the משנה mishnah says
you own ten dollars of my ox. No, logically, I should own
forty dollars of your ox and you should own fifty dollars of
my ox, right? So again, by saying that no, the conclusion is
that we don't own each others'. You just, the one who suffered
more damage owns that part part of the ox of the one
who did more damage. It again says that we're looking at this
as the only damage that occurred was the difference of the damage,
right? So one way or the other, there's a huge חידוש chiddush
in this משנה. mishnah. We do not look at it as two
separate acts. If it was two separate acts, you'd own part of
his ox and he'd own part of yours. If it was two
separate acts, you'd first divide what the תם tam did in half
and then you'd figure out the full amount that the מועד muad
did. But we're not saying that. We're saying if they were started
at the same time, we only look at the difference. Okay, that's
a huge חידוש. chiddush. גמרא Gemara never even explains why, but that's
a huge חידוש. chiddush. Okay.
Now it says like this. Okay. וכן שני אנשים שחבלו זה בזה,
V'chen shenei anashim shechavlu zeh bazeh, two people that were that injured
one another intentionally, inflicted injury, משלמים במותר נזק שלם. meshalmim b'motar nezek
shalem. You pay the difference, the full amount. Okay, you should also
pay, I mean it's sort of ignoring right now the other issue
about the doctor bills and the צער tza'ar and all of that.
אדם במועד ומועד באדם, Adam b'muad v'muad b'adam, now let's say it
was a man fighting an ox or an ox fighting a man.
So they're both so if they're both מועד, muad, if the ox
is a מועד, muad, so משלמים במותר נזק שלם, meshalmim b'motar nezek
shalem, you look at the difference and it pays the full. אדם
בתם ותם באדם, Adam b'tam v'tam b'adam, let's say he was fighting
against a תם tam ox, אדם בתם adam b'tam so if the
person did more against the תם tam than the תם tam ox
did against him, משלמים במותר נזק שלם. meshalmim b'motar nezek shalem. תם
באדם, Tam b'adam, if the תם tam ox did more against the
person, משלם במותר חצי נזק, meshaleim b'motar chatzi nezek, you pay half
of the difference. Again,
not that you half it first
and then figure it out. No, you look at the difference and
you pay half of the difference. Okay. רבי עקיבא אומר אף תם
שחבל באדם משלם במותר נזק שלם. Rabbi Akiva omer af tam shechaval
b'adam meshaleim b'motar nezek shalem. This is the רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
we quoted way back in the first פרק perek that he believes
that a תם tam ox that pays half, that's only if it
gores another ox. But if a תם tam ox gores a person,
it pays full. Okay, and we're going to see in the גמרא
Gemara why that is. We're going to read the גמרא Gemara and
then I want to go back and say an important point that
the ראש Rosh said about earlier in the משנה. mishnah. Let's see
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. כמשפט הזה יעשה לו.
Kamishpat hazeh yeaseh lo. So basically what you have in the תורה,
Torah, it speaks about if an ox, if an ox gores somebody,
it says כי יגח שור איש או אשה ki yigach shor ish
o ishah whatever. It says about if an ox kills somebody, it
says והמית איש או אשה השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת, v'hemit ish
o ishah hashor yisakel v'gam ba'alav yumat, okay, אם כופר יושת עליו
im kofer yushat alav right? ונתן פדיון נפשו ככל אשר יושת עליו,
v'natan pidyon nafsho k'chol asher yushat alav, או בן יגח או בת
יגח, כמשפט הזה יעשה לו. o ben yigach o bat yigach kamishpat
hazeh yeaseh lo? Okay. This is about כמשפט הזה יעשה לו. kamishpat
hazeh yeaseh lo. Okay. So this is a case about a case
about killing, killing a person. Killing a person. And then afterwards it
speaks about about a שור נגח. shor nagach. כי יגח שור איש
את שור רעהו. Ki yigach shor ish et shor re'eihu. כי יגח
שור איש את שור רעהו. Ki yigach shor ish et shor re'eihu.
Then it says וחצו את כספו, v'chatzu et kaspo, okay. And then
it has so first it has a case about so this is
a case about killing a שור, shor, and it has תם tam
and then it has מועד. muad. Okay, that's the order that the
פרשיות parshiyot appear in the תורה. Torah. First killing a person, then
goring another ox, if it's a תם tam it pays half, if
it's a מועד muad it pays full. Now, what's this או בן
יגח או בת יגח O ben yigach o bat yigach, כמשפט הזה
יעשה לו? kamishpat hazeh yeaseh lo. Like why should I think it's
different? If it kills somebody you pay a כופר, kofer, if it
kills a, you know, a son or a daughter you should also
you do the same thing. What's the חידוש? chiddush? So the חידוש,
chiddush, the פשט, pshat, the פשט pshat wants you know a little
about, about that, about you whatever about the code of Hammurabi is
that the. of the Code of Hammurabi, it says that if an
ox gores another person, if a person's ox gores and kills the
child of another person, then you kill that person's child. Okay. So
the תורה Torah *Torah* is saying no. Okay? That even if it's
killing a child, you're going to pay a כפר *Kofer*, you're not
going to go ahead and kill this other person's children. But the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* doesn't understand it this way. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
sort of says why do you need like assumes why do you
need this extra פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*? And it assumes that this case
of או בן יגח או בת יגח *O ven yigach o vat
yigach* is not talking about goring and killing a child of another
person. It's talking about goring and injuring the child of another person.
So this issue that's being dealt with in our משנה Mishna *Mishna*,
when an ox gores and injures a person, okay, and the question
is going to be רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says you pay full
and the חכמים *Chakhamim* say that you pay half. They understand that
that's the case of this case of או בן יגח או בת
יגח *O ven yigach o vat yigach*. It gored and injured a
person. You do the same law. So what law do you do?
Are you going to pay half? Are you going to pay full?
So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. תנו
רבנן *Tano Rabbanan*. כמשפט הזה יעשה לו *Kemishpat hazeh yaaseh lo*. כמשפט
שור בשור כך משפט שור באדם *Kemishpat shor beshor kach mishpat shor
beadam*. כמשפט
הזה *Kemishpat hazeh* means if it gores and injures a child or
whatever, any person, you do like the normal law like the normal
law about a goring ox, which is half for the first three
times, full afterwards. Okay. כמשפט שור בשור כך משפט שור באדם *Kemishpat
shor beshor kach mishpat shor beadam*. מה שור בשור תם משלם חצי
נזק nezek מועד נזק שלם *Mah shor beshor tam meshalem chatzi nezek
muad nezek shalem*. אף שור באדם *Af shor beadam*, so similarly if
it gores a person and it injures them, תם משלם חצי נזק
מועד נזק שלם *Tam meshalem chatzi nezek muad nezek shalem*. Fine. רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* אומר *Omer* no. כמשפט הזה *Kemishpat hazeh* כתחתון *Ketachton*
ולא כעליון *Velo keelyon*. No. What it says is כמשפט הזה יעשה
לו *Kemishpat hazeh yaaseh lo*. So the כמשפט הזה *Kemishpat hazeh* means
the second case because here we are notice here. First we talk
about killing a person and it does it תם *Tam*. Right? This
is when it kills a person in a case of a תם
*Tam*. This is killing a person as a תם *Tam*. So that
case you basically kill the ox. Okay but and then אם כפר
יושת עליו *Im kofer yushat alav*, this is a case of killing
a person as a מועד *Muad*. Okay. It's structured the same way.
Killing a person, first it deals with תם *Tam* then מועד *Muad*,
goring an ox תם *Tam* and מועד *Muad*. So when it says
כמשפט הזה יעשה לו *Kemishpat hazeh yaaseh lo*, it's like the most
recent case we discussed. The case of כפר *Kofer* is only by
a מועד *Muad*. So if it gores a person and injures them,
you do like the second case. You treat it like a מועד
*Muad*, you do not treat it like a תם *Tam*. All right?
Clear how he's reading that? כמשפט כתחתון *Kemishpat ketachton* ולא כעליון *Velo
keelyon*. Like the second case we've been dealing with, the most proximate
case, it's treated like a מועד *Muad*, it's not treated like a
תם *Tam*. יכול משלם מן העליה *Yachol meshalem min haaliya*? Maybe that
you pay actually like from cash, not from the body of the
ox because normally when you pay full you pay from cash. תלמוד
לומר *Talmud lomar* יעשה לו *Yaaseh lo*, due to it, the ox.
מגופו migupo, משלם ואינו משלם מן העליה *Migufo meshalem veeino meshalem min
haaliya*. So it's an interesting hybrid. You pay full but only out
of the body of the ox. Okay. ורבנן זה למה לי *Verabbanan
zeh lamah li*? Why did the rabbis say זה *Zeh*? Because it's
not just כמשפט יעשה לו *Kemishpat yaaseh lo*. They say it means
treat it like a normal goring ox. זה *Zeh* seems to limit
like only like one law which רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says is
only the law of a מועד *Muad*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no. לפטרה מארבע דברים *Lepatrah mearba devarim*. To tell you treat
it fully like an ox, don't treat it like a person injured
a person where you pay those additional payments. It's only like an
ox goring and it's only going to pay damages. ורבי עקיבא לפטרה
מארבע דברים מנא ליה *Verabbi Akiva lepatrah mearba devarim minaleh*? Where does
he know that? נפקא ליה *Nafkah leh* מאיש כי יתן מום בעמיתו
*Meish ki yiten mum beamito*. If a person inflicts damage on another
person, כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו *Kaasher asah ken yaaseh lo*, עין
תחת עין שן תחת שן *Ayin tachat ayin shen tachat shen* etc.
And from some of those extra words we learn some of those
additional payments like צער *Tzaar* and like you know צער *Tzaar*. So
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says איש בעמיתו ולא שור בעמיתו *Ish beamito velo
shor beamito*. Those additional payments are only when it's one person injuring
another person, not an ox injuring a person. ורבנן *Verabbanan*, why couldn't
the rabbis learn it from there? אימא ההיא הוה אמינא צער לחודא
*Eima hahee havah amina tzaar lechuda*. Because all we learn from that
פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* is צער *Tzaar*. So I would have said fine,
you're exempt from צער *Tzaar*. אבל ריפוי ושבת *Aval ripuy veshevet*, but
maybe the other payments which are learned from a different פסוק pasuk:
*Pasuk* like you know like doctor bills and the fact that you're
out of work, אימא ליתן ליה *Eima litten leh*, maybe you do
have to pay when an ox gores a person. קא משמע לן
*Kamashma lan* that you don't. Okay. So כמשפט הזה יעשה לו *Kemishpat
hazeh yaaseh lo*, we're saying this means an ox gores a person.
The rabbis say it means you treat it like a normal goring
ox and you pay half. And the כמשפט הזה *Kemishpat hazeh* is
saying and you won't pay like an ox case, you don't pay
additional payments like if a person injured another person. And רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* says כמשפט הזה *Kemishpat hazeh* means like this most recent
case of a מועד *Muad*. When a person an ox gores a
person we treat it like a מועד *Muad* and you pay full.
Okay. So that's an issue that we had quoted earlier about the
payment of an ox goring a person. Now before we leave אדם
המזיק *Adam Hamazik* and now focus fully on the goring ox, I
just have to end by telling you an important ראש Rosh *Rosh*
that deals with this משנה mishnah *Mishna* about two people fighting, okay,
which it says that you figure out the difference. So just turn
for... So turn for a moment if you can find this, I
want, just want to read the bit inside to the ראש Rosh
in the back here, it's right after the גמרא, Gemara it's... it's
סימן י״ג, Siman Yud Gimmel, פרק שלישי, Perek Shlishi, I probably should
have just Xeroxed off this page. Anyway, in my גמרא Gemara it's
on page קכ״ו. Kuf Chaf Vav. All right? So I just want
to read this very briefly. It says like this. It says...
So
he says like this: So first he says if one ox starts
and the other reacts, it's כל המשנה בחברו ושינה בו kol hamishaneh
bachaveiro v'shina bo and the ox that's reacting after having first been
gored, the owner is exempt because the ox was just responding in
kind. And then he says, if you look about six lines in
in this סימן י״ג Siman Yud Gimmel by the letter זיין Zayin
in brackets he says like this: דאפילו באדם אית ליה רשות לשנויי.
d'afilu b'adam it lei reshus l'shanei. וכן שני אנשים v'chen shenei anashim
two people נמי מאישתא אתקלו כאחד nami m'aishe itkelu k'echad they started
fighting at the same time או אחר זמן o acher zman or
first one guy, ראובן Reuven beat up שמעון Shimon and then later
שמעון Shimon came and beat up ראובן. Reuven. אבל אם התחיל האחד
aval im hitchil ha-echad but if one guy... if ראובן Reuven started
beating up שמעון Shimon and then שמעון Shimon fought back השני פטור
hasheini patur שמעון Shimon is exempt, you're just fighting back to defend
yourself. ואף על גב דלא שייך באדם כל המשנה בחברו ושינה בו
פטור ve'af al gav d'lo shayach b'adam kol hamishaneh bachaveiro v'shina bo
patur okay, even though we know we don't say that just because
you did something to me that entitles me to go ahead like
you know and do something to you, but that doesn't matter here
because here you're defending yourself. ואפילו על עסקי ממון אמרינן לעיל מאה
פנדי בפנדי דמריה למחייה ve'afilu al iskei mamon amrinan l'eil meiah pandei
b'pandei d'marei l'machei remember we said I could even use violence, remember
the discussion of taking the law into my own hands? I can
even use violence to protect my property. So of course I can
use violence to protect myself. You're beating me up, I can use
violence to beat you up to protect myself. All right? Now of
course the question becomes at what stage is my use of violence
protecting myself and what stage is my use of the violence of
you hit me now I'm going to beat you up, right, you
know, so what stage does it become protecting and what stage does
it become something else?
The standard that we have in the criminal liability of רודף rodef
is only authorized to use
the necessary force, so he's going to get to that, exactly. So
he says... so let's take a look, he says: והכי נמי אמרינן
וקיימא לן לעיל וקצתה כפה בכל דהצולה בדבר אחר v'hachi nami amrinan
u'k'minan l'eil v'katsetah kapa b'chol hatsolei davar acher right,
that when this woman pays בושת boshet for grabbing the privates of
this other man beating her husband up, that's when she had an
option. אבל אם אינה יכולה פטורה aval im einah yachola paturah but
if she didn't have an option she can use physical force to
protect her husband. כיון שהתחיל להכות את בעלה kivan she-hitchil l'hakos es
ba'alah if this other guy started it. וכל שכן שהמוכה עצמו פטור
v'chol she-kein she-hamukei atzmo patur certainly the guy who's being beaten up
is allowed to defend himself. ומיהו u'mihu now here we get to
your point צריך לומר דאם היה יכול להציל עצמו בחבלה מועטת tzarich
lomar d'im hayah yachol l'hatsil atzmo b'chabalah mu'etes because of exactly this
גמרא Gemara about the woman defending her husband כשחבל בו הרבה חייב
k'shechaval bo harbei chayav if you could have done lesser injury but
you used excessive force, you're liable. So it doesn't give you a
license to now just beat the guy up. It gives you a
license to do what's necessary to protect yourself. You can use force
to protect yourself, but it cannot be excessive force. Okay? I have
no idea that you
might be killed by the guy.
Right, okay, so if you can make that as a legitimate argument,
I really was afraid for my life and I thought I had
no option, right? I mean, but like, you know, דוב Dov was
saying apparently this is true in secular law as well, a court
would have to assess if that's a reasonable claim. Okay?
incapacitated the guy and then continues to beat him.
Right. Right. So then he says, okay, and then he goes on,
but now he has an interesting thing, if you skip down about
five lines, he says like this... or two lines down... like where
it says סנהדרין ע״ד, Sanhedrin Ayin Dalet, right below there in parentheses:
וכן הדין אם אדם רואה שמכין את אביו v'hen hadin im adam
roeh she-makin es aviv like we asked this before when it said
עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, avid inish dina l'nafshei, a woman protecting her
husband how much is it your... what does it mean to protect
yourself, if it's protecting people close to you? So he says if
somebody sees somebody beating up his father או בניו o banav or
his children או אחיו o achiv or his brother והכה את המכה
v'hikah es hamakeh and you intervene to protect your family member כדי
להציל קרובו פטור kedei l'hatsil k'rovo patur you're exempt. כמו אשה המצלת
את בעלה k'mo ishah hamatseiles es ba'alah like the woman who saves
her husband. אם אינה יכולה להציל על ידי דבר אחר im einah
yachola l'hatsil al yedei davar acher so he's learning out from this
case of the woman intervening for her husband, you're allowed to use
force to protect your property and protect your person and those of
the people immediately connected to you. Now how far? What if it's
my second cousin? What if it's my uncle? I'm serious, like what's
the stage? So then he says, oh what if it's a stranger?
We normally know if I see somebody who's in the process of
attempting to murder someone, I can intervene to protect the innocent victim.
But let's say it's not murder, let's say it's just somebody's being
beaten up. Can I use force to protect the victim? Like משה,
Moshe, right, except משה Moshe just used words the second time. When
it was the Egyptian he used force. When it was the two
Jews, he just gave... he didn't use force. So that's what he
says, he says: וכן אם רואה אדם שישראל מכה את חברו v'hen
im roeh adam she-yisrael makeh es chaveiro and so too if a
person sees a ישראל Yisrael beating his friend ואין יכול להציל אם
לא שיכה את המכה v'ein yachol l'hatsil im lo she-yakeh es hamakeh
and you can't save him unless you hit the attacker אף על
פי שאין המכה הוא מכת נפש af al pi she-ein hamakeh u'makas
nefesh even though the attacker is not dealing a death blow. even
though it's not going to kill the guy, so it's not a
רודף, rodef, מותר להכות המכה mutar le-hakot ha-makeh להפרישו מאיסורא. le-hafrisho me-issura.
So he now, he can't do it based on the right for
self-protection
and עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina lenafshei because you're no
longer self-protecting,
right? But what he does is he bases it on this idea
of you're allowed to use force to stop somebody from doing an
איסור. issur. Okay, now that's a little bit funny, because he only,
logically you would like to say I'm allowed to intervene to protect
the innocent victim as opposed to I'm intervening because that guy is
doing an עבירה aveirah and I'm using force to stop... it creates
a different, you can imagine different consequences from framing it in that
way. Okay, and you could logically say that when my property is
being threatened, if it's not my property or my family's, then I
have to let the court handle it. Then it's not... otherwise it's
like undermines the justice system. You can't say עביד איניש דינא לאחרינא,
avid inish dina le-achreim, עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina lenafshei.
Or what you would have wanted to say is if it's somebody
being physically injured, I can't wait for the courts, right? That's the
case like the גמרא Gemara, says. That's a case of like הפסד,
hefsed, like there's... the person is not going to recover the reality
of having been injured and having had his bones broken. So there
I should be allowed to intervene just for... that should have been,
I would have said a logical extension of the idea of רודף.
rodef. You have רודף rodef after a נפש, nefesh, and רודף rodef
of bodily injury. And logically I think you should have been able
to say the same thing. So the רא"ש Rosh. wants to say
the same thing, but it's interesting that he uses... for him the
available sort of halachic mechanism is this idea of stopping the guy
from doing an עבירה, aveirah, which is a different mechanism. Let's say
it's a קטן. katan. Let's say I see a קטן katan that's
got, you know, that's beating up somebody else, right? Can I say,
well am I allowed to stop a קטן katan from doing an
עבירה? aveirah? Right? I mean there's a problem framing it in terms
of the עבירה aveirah of the perpetrator rather than the, rather than
protecting the innocent victim. Did you want to say something?
First of all, if you have to, if you have to use
these mechanisms, so what's the mechanism for protecting yourself? I mean, it's
obvious you have to protect yourself, right?
Right, that's the עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, avid inish dina lenafshei, some
there's this presumption that you have a right to protect yourself.
Why am I allowed to protect myself?
Well, right. The גמרא Gemara never spells that out, meaning the גמרא
Gemara sort of makes that implicit when it discusses the logic of,
what do you call it, of בבא דמחתרת. Baba de-machtarta. The reason
that you can kill the בעל המחתרת ba’al ha-machtarta is because he's
coming to, to take your property. You're allowed to stand up to
defend your property and then he wants to kill you and you
kill him. But the question is, well why don't you just let
him take your property? What allows you to turn that whole case
into a case of like... you know, so there is a presumption
there which the גמרא Gemara, never sort of gives a פסוק pasuk
as a basis for it, that you are allowed to defend yourself
and your property. But yeah, I mean you're right, it never sort
of... it assumes it. That's what the assumption of עביד איניש דינא
לנפשיה avid inish dina lenafshei is, but it never like spells out
what that's based on.
He says cases of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, avid inish dina lenafshei,
cases of נזק was that the court would have reached the same
conclusion, but if you had waited through protocol, you'd lost all your
stuff. Exactly. Well, not lost, meaning the immediacy of...
right, so there was a loss and that's why the גמרא Gemara,
says when there is איכא פסידא, ikka pesseida, everybody agrees. And that's,
and I would have said the same thing, I would have said,
and I mentioned this when we did this, that therefore any case
of physical injury, even if I can get compensated afterwards, is always
a case of פסידא. pesseida. Right, right, I agree. And I think
that the רא"ש is basically saying that. You always have a right
to protect yourself against injury. The problem is that עביד איניש דינא
avid inish dina is limited to לנפשיה. lenafshei. Okay, so I don't
have, if I see somebody about to damage your property and there's
no way you're going to recover the loss, am I allowed to
use physical force to stop him? Or would we say, no, that's
going to undermine the justice system. We allow you to do it
to protect yourself but not to go ahead for some other person,
right? It's נעבעך nebach that that guy's going to be out the
money, but we can't let everybody around doing their own little vigilante
justice. Okay, but you would still think that there would be more
license, it wouldn't be limited to לנפשיה lenafshei when you're dealing about
protecting somebody's physical person, right?
In general, you can use force to prevent someone from doing an
איסור. issur.
Yes, I mean that does come up in the גמרא, Gemara or
the גמרא Gemara sort of said that in our עביד איניש דינא
לנפשיה avid inish dina lenafshei and it comes up in the גמרא
Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin also about a case about רודף rodef to
do an עבירה, aveirah, not exactly רודף rodef to kill or whatever.
But yes, there's questions about what are the limits of that also,
right? How much force and whatever, and how do you weigh what...
so all of those are relevant questions. But anyway, so it's obviously
a very important רא"ש. It's surprising that it's not more explicit in
the גמרא, Gemara but I really, very important I think like
a second part to our discussion of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid
inish dina lenafshei. Okay, let's look now back at the גמרא, Gemara
משנה mishnah at the bottom of ל"ג ע"ב. Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet.
שור ששוה
מנה שנגף שור ששוה מאתים ואין הנבלה יפה כלום נוטל את השור.
Shor she-shava maneh she-nagaf shor she-shava matayim ve-ein ha-neveilah yafah klum, notel
et ha-shor. So here we have the idea that you pay half
but... so you have a two hundred dollar... a one hundred dollar
ox goring a two hundred dollar ox. So the two hundred... so
half of it is a hundred, full... that's towards the full value
of the goring ox. So therefore the injured party takes the entire
ox. Okay, now so that's basically saying you pay half. It's limited
to the value of the ox. Presumably if the damage was a
hundred and twenty, if it was two hundred and forty and half
of... One twenty, he'd be out the extra, so that's one point
that it's limited, it's מגופו, migupo. but the bigger חידוש chiddush of
the משנה mishnah is not that he gets paid a hundred and
it's limited to the value of the ox. The bigger חידוש chiddush
of the משנה mishnah is he just takes the ox. And this
is going to be a question of how much do we mean
מגופו. Okay,
so because פסוק says ומכרו את השור החי וחצו את כספו. u-machru
et ha-shor ha-chai ve-chatzu et kaspo. So what does that mean? Who
is selling the ox? Do I actually, the injured party, own half
of your ox as soon as it gores my ox? So that's
our משנה mishnah, sounds like yes. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. This is going to be a debate of Rabbi Akiva and
Rabbi Ishmael. גמרא Gemara says like this: מתניתין מני רבי עקיבא היא.
Masnissin mani? Rabbi Akiva hi. Our משנה that says you just take
the ox is Rabbi Akiva. דתניא ותנא ברייתא: De-tanya ve-tana baraita: ויושם
השור בבית דין, Ve-yusham ha-shor be-veit din, דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi
Ishmael. Rabbi Ishmael says you take the goring ox into בית דין,
beit din, you assess its value, and that's how much the guy
owes. He owes half of the damage up to the value of
the ox. But he doesn't become a part owner in the ox,
certainly not automatically. Okay, that's what Rabbi Ishmael says. Rabbi Akiva אומר
הוחלט השור. omer Huchlat ha-shor. No, the ox is directly given over
to the injured party or that percentage of it is given over
to the injured party. He becomes a part owner. Okay, now במאי
קמיפלגי? be-mai kamifligi? What's this debate about? Rabbi Ishmael סבר בעל חוב
הוא. savar baal chov hu. The injured party is just a creditor,
he just, you know, is owed money. וזוזי הוא דמסיק ליה. Ve-zuzei
hu d’masik lei. It's like he lent money to the, you know,
money, you know, he has a debt against or whatever, money is
owed to him from the injuring party, and it's just a debt.
Okay, and we'll see what the role of the ox is other
than limiting the amount of the debt. Rabbi Akiva סבר שותפין נינהו.
savar shutfin ninhu. As soon as his ox is injured, he becomes
a partner in the attacking ox. וקמיפלגי בהאי קרא. Ve-kamifligi be-hai kra.
And they're debating how to read the פסוק: ומכרו
את השור החי וחצו את כספו. u-machru et ha-shor ha-chai ve-chatzu et
kaspo. You sell the living ox and you split its value. But
the case in this תורה Torah is that the oxen were worth
the same amount. A two hundred dollar ox gored a two hundred
dollar ox. Okay, the
the gored ox got killed, is worth zero. So now you owe
a hundred dollars. The goring ox was worth two hundred, so they
become equal partners, right? So you get it, if the oxen were
worth the same, right? Right, if if Shimon's ox and Reuven's ox,
whatever, were the same and the one is completely made worthless, then
half of that, then they become half owners in the goring ox.
Yes.
Suppose the question if the נבילה neveilah is worth something, then we
say
בעלי מטפלין בנבילה. ba-alei m’taplin bi-neveilah. Right? And then the price goes
down.
Right, you only get half of the difference of it. Right, exactly.
Okay.
So Rabbi Ishmael סבר, savar, now who is the תורה Torah talking
to? Rabbi Ishmael סבר לבית דין קמזהירא רחמנא. savar le-beit din kama-zhira
Rachmana. The the תורה Torah is talking to the בית דין. beit
din. Okay, the בית דין beit din should sell the ox and
split the difference, which basically means, you know, Reuven owes Shimon money,
okay, so Reuven's ox has to be sold by the court and
the court will then pay it off. Okay, but it's not that
Shimon now owns the ox. בית דין beit din has to make
sure that Reuven pays
Shimon. Rabbi Akiva סבר לניזק ומזיק מזהירא רחמנא. savar le-nizak u-mazik mazira
Rachmana. No, the תורה Torah is saying you guys, Reuven and Shimon,
sell your ox and split it. So if they are selling the
ox, that means that Shimon is also part of the sale of
the ox. Means that Shimon is now a part owner in the
ox. Okay, so מאי בינייהו? mai beineihu? What would be a difference
whether you say it's a debt or it's a part owner? So
there's a huge amount of differences. Okay, the first difference is, well
let's just read the גמרא's Gemara difference. מאי בינייהו הקדישו ניזק איכא
בינייהו. Mai beineihu? Hikdisho nizak ika beineihu. If Shimon, Shimon is the
one whose ox was gored, after the ox was gored, he and
now let's say it's the case of the משנה, okay, we won't
even make them partners. It's the case where it was a hundred
dollar damage and Reuven's ox was worth a hundred dollars. Okay, so
if Shimon now owns the ox, Shimon could say, I מקדיש, makdish,
it's my ox. Okay, if he's just owed money, he obviously can't
be מקדיש. makdish. There's a much easier נפקא מינה nafka mina or
immediate one, I mean תוספות Tosfos says it could have listed a
dozen נפקא מינה. nafka minas. A more immediate one is Reuven says,
I don't want to give you the ox, I'll pay you the
hundred dollars. Okay, so if basically it's just a debt, we're going
to see in a minute, it might be a debt with a
particular lien on this ox, but any debt I if I owe
you money I am always entitled to give you cash. Okay, so
so therefore another big נפקא מינה nafka mina is that the guy
just wants to pay cash, right? Is he allowed to or does
the guy say, no I'm sorry, I already own part of your
ox. All right. So בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. ba-ei minei Rava
mei-Rav Nachman. Now רבא Rava asked the following question of רב נחמן:
Rav Nachman: מכרו מזיק לרבי ישמעאל מהו? Macharo mazik le-Rabbi Ishmael mahu?
Let's say Reuven sold the ox. Now if according to, according to
Rabbi, according to Rabbi Akiva, Reuven can't sell the ox, Shimon already
owns it. But according to Rabbi Ishmael where where Reuven just owes
money, so maybe he should be entitled to sell the ox, he
only owes Shimon money. כיון דאמר רבי ישמעאל בעל חוב הוא, Keivan
d'amar Rabbi Yishmael ba'al chov hu, since רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says
that basically שמעון Shimon is just owed money, so וזוזי הוא דמסיק
ליה v'zuzei hu d'masik lei and basically he just is owed money,
מכור, machur, so now ראובן Reuven can sell the ox, he'll pay
שמעון Shimon money. או דלמא O dilma or do we say, no,
the היזק hezek and how much rights to the ox does it
have according to רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Ishmael? או דלמא כיון דמשעבד ליה
לניזק, O dilma keivan d'meshabad lei le-nizak, since שמעון Shimon has a
lien on that ox, because it's not just סתם stam ראובן Reuven
owes him money. ראובן Reuven owes him money and he has a
right to sell the ox to get some money. Okay, so how
much, like the פסוק is also saying ומכרו את השור החי, v'machru
et ha-shor ha-chai, which means I can demand that we sell that
ox so that I can get paid. So how much, how strong
are my rights to that ox? I don't own it, but I
have a lien on it and I can use it to get
my money. How strong are my rights? Do we say כיון דמשעבד
ליה לניזק, keivan d'meshabad lei le-nizak, since it's encumbered to the ניזק,
Nizak, לאו כל כמיניה, lav kol keminei, ראובן Reuven does not have
a right to sell it. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, אינו מכור. eino machur. Yeah, you're right, ראובן Reuven can't sell
it. It's like he, you know, שמעון Shimon has, doesn't own the
ox, but he has a complete sort of right to make sure
that it gets liquidated and that he can get the money out
of it. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
והתניא מכור מכור, ve-ha tanya machur machur, but a ברייתא braita says
if שמעון Shimon sells it, if ראובן Reuven sells it, it is
sold.
So, so fine, what it means is it's sold, but חוזר וגובה.
chozer v'goveh. So ראובן Reuven sold it to לוי, Levi, שמעון Shimon
can now go and collect it from לוי. Levi. So it was
sold, it's not that the sale was void, it still is ראובן's
Reuven ox, but שמעון Shimon has a lien on it. So ראובן
Reuven sells it and שמעון Shimon goes and שמעון Shimon collects it.
So the גמרא says, and presumably then לוי Levi gets his money
back from ראובן, Reuven, מאחר שחוזר וגובה למה מכור, m'acher she-chozer v'goveh
lama machur, or למה מכור? lema machur? So I don't get it,
if שמעון Shimon can just go ahead and collect it, שמעון Shimon
can go and collect it even after the sale, for what purpose
does לוי Levi own it?
לרדיא. L'radya. So that he can use it to plow his field
until שמעון Shimon decides to come and collect it and to exercise
his lien, I own it. I legitimately bought it, it's got a
lien on it, right? It's like any, like land that has a
lien. I buy the land, I can use the land, if somebody's
going to collect the land with his debt, he'll take it from
me at that point, but until that point I have a right
to use it. Okay, so it's ראובן's, Reuven he can sell it,
but שמעון Shimon has a lien on it that allows שמעון Shimon
to go and collect it. Even though normally liens only apply to
land and not to cattle, here the תורה Torah says you have
a right to that ox. It's not, you don't own it, but
you have a right to have it sold for you to get
your money. Okay, so the גמרא says
שמע מינה, shmaminah, do we learn from this a general principle that
לוה ומוכר מטלטלין בית דין גובין להן? loveh u-mocher metaltelin beit din
govin la-hen? That if you owe money and you sell your cattle,
that the בית דין beit din can go ahead and collect that
cattle from the third parties? Meaning should we learn that, that liens
apply to cattle? I mean liens normally don't apply to cattle. So
the גמרא says, no, שאני התם דכמאן דשוייה אפותיקי דמי. shani hatam
d'keman d'asav apotiki dami. Here it's different. Here it's like you have
an explicit lien on it. And אפותיקי apotiki is not just a
generic lien which only applies to land and not to cattle. אפותיקי
apotiki is we explicitly say your car is mortgaged, you know, for
this loan. And that case, even though it's cattle and you sold
your car, I can go and collect the car. So here the
תורה Torah says, the תורה Torah gives the אפותיקי. apotiki. The תורה
Torah says ומכרו את השור החי. v'machru et ha-shor ha-chai. So the
תורה says wherever happens to that ox, you're going to have a
right to collect it and to use it to pay off your
loan. So the גמרא says, one minute, that still violates normal principles.
ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, רבא Rava says, עשה עבדו אפותיקי ומכרו בית
דין גובין הימנו. asa avdo apotiki u-machro beit din govin himenu. If
you make an explicit, like, lien on your slave and you sold
it, בית דין beit din will exercise that lien. Okay, שור אפותיקי
ומכרו אין בית דין גובין הימנו. shor apotiki u-machro ein beit din
govin himenu. But if you tried to do it on your ox
and you sold it, בית דין beit din won't exercise the lien.
So you cannot make and presumably because an עבד eved is like
land, it's clear there's some cattle that cannot have a lien on
it. It's not fair to the purchasers. The reason land can have
a lien is because, you know, it's very, you know, it's in
a fixed place whatever people can find out about it and so
on. Anyway, so this still violates some of our general rules. The
גמרא says, no, it doesn't violate our rules. עבד מאי טעמא? Eved
mai ta'ama? Why do we allow there to be an explicit lien
on a slave? משום דאית ליה קלא, mishum d'is lei kala, because
people can find out about slaves. Okay, slaves are important enough sort
of piece of, you know, property as it was that people will
know if they're encumbered or not. Okay, and therefore we figure that
when you do explicit, people who are, you know, buyer beware and
people will be able to investigate and find out. Normal cattle, people
won't be able to find out. But that's just normal cattle. האי
נמי כיון דנגח קלא אית ליה, Hai nami keivan d'nagach kala is
lei, in this case, since the, since it gored, that's very unusual
to have a goring ox. קלא אית ליה, Kala is lei, people,
it has a, it, you know, the word gets out. תורא נגחנא
קרו ליה. Tora nagchana karu lei. People call it, oh, ראובן's Reuven
goring ox. Okay, so basically what's interesting is rather than just Rather
than just say it's a גזירת הכתוב *gezeiras hakasuv* the גמרא *Gemara*
wants this to fit into its normal principles. So what it says
is, for רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* the ניזק *nizak* automatically owns it,
and for רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* no, the ניזק *nizak* is owed
money but he has a explicit lien on it and מכל מקום
*mikol makom* he has a right to force בית דין *Beis Din*
to sell it, and that means that even if it's sold to
another person, normally you don't have a lien on cattle, but it's
possible that it can happen, and therefore this is considered to be
a case of a lien on cattle that works, and that allows
him to go ahead and to collect it even sold to another
person. So we're going to continue tomorrow to figure out the differences
between רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*.